it really is I swear my room is cleaner
all right I we're somebody asked a
question um it is it's getting cleaner
stop giving me crap about my room it's
it's a mess it is but you know what
because I'm getting ready for the
adventure of a lifetime so stay tuned
for that Odin project the Odin
project uh o i n and you can go look it
up what do I think of the Odin project
um the Odin project came to my attention
several years years ago actually I want
to say it was probably 2018 or 2019 and
I've been following it with intense
interest for a long time um when the
Odin project first came out I was
extremely Pro Odin project um I was
really mostly because I like that the
Odin project
has essentially opened sourced or crowd
sourced if you will education
particularly in the web development
although as I understand it Odin project
is not just web
development um but my I had I had two
negative Impressions about the Odin
project so um you know I'll I'll I'll
just say it straight out I think the
Ogen Odin project is a good use of your
time um because I I feel like it's
something that can be contributed to and
it it's you know it's not proprietary
and they um you know there's lots of
good ideas in there I it's the same
thing I said about free code Camp except
for the problem with free code Camp is
the same sort of problem with with with
the Odin project um as I've said before
for
Education uh things uh tend to you know
not work they it's kind of sad um and to
contrast that really quickly there is
there was a series called pyth on the
hard way which I should probably do
which this guy basically I mean he made
a book that was like super skinny it was
like this teeny tiny little book and it
was like okay now go learn this now go
learn this and do this and make a
project that does this now go learn this
and do this and make a project that does
this and the the book basically said
here's all the things you need to learn
go learn them and it didn't try to teach
them the thing um but you know where are
you going to learn it you you you got to
see somebody doing it right so uh my the
bottom line on the Odin project is I
don't think uh I I look I just I don't
like for Education things I I don't I I
think that you can get that experience
by more directly by identifying the
specific skills that you need and that
is my biggest there's the two negatives
I told you and that is the the first
negative about the Odin project is that
it doesn't Target um it's not specific
enough right um and and that that
bothers me right because the more
removed you are from practicing an
actual skill that's you're going to
perform on the job um the the less you
know I suppose relevance it has the less
U uh focus it has um so to be completely
so for example what would you do instead
of the Odin project right um so as I
understand it the Odin project is I
haven't I haven't even looked at it
within the last two or three years so I
I could be totally wrong and if I am
pleased yell at in the comments um
somebody yelled at me about preo Camp
saying it's the videos are are fantastic
I just watched the video channel and
it's very informational and that's cool
um you know you share again you are in
charge of your own education you can
tell me to shut up and do whatever you
want that that's if you know always the
takeaway is you are in charge don't let
anybody else anybody else tell you what
to do you are the one in charge of your
own learning and you're the only one who
knows you um so anyway and having said
that the odm project has lots of there's
lots of IDE you could get there but I
was told that it was was primarily
focused on webd and then the question is
well what kind of webdev right um you
know what are we what what are we doing
there right if we're if we're just um so
I mean at least it's free right and and
there's a whole video I just made
recently about boot camps don't you know
don't give your money to a boot camp
usually and please go watch that um and
so the odm Project's primary positive
thing is it's free
uh free C Camp is free um they try to
sell you stuff on the side there like
most free projects uh OD project doesn't
have any of that and it's completely
driven by the community um which is nice
um so you know the the the first one I
would say is is is it it only covers you
know webd and it may not cover the web
dev that you want to do or the type that
you need to do and and the fact that it
covers webd period um I think I I think
I think the statistics bear out that
webd we'll talk about hun devs next um
uh it's written like a Wiki right um uh
there's a lot of reading simple
exercises small projects yeah um and
they do I do like I'm glad you mention
that um so because because the odm
project does kind of incrementally build
on stuff and it as I remember it it it
tells you about the project but it
doesn't have an interactive web page
that says you know gold star go on to
the next one gold star go on to the next
one having you not learn anything that's
that was my experience with recod Camp
uh not my experience the people who I
helped um their experience so the fact
that that the Odin project tells you
stuff uh to do and then lets you do your
own evaluation and do it and then you
know form your own Community to validate
that you know what you're doing all
things that I strongly believe in and
that it's it's it's driven by Community
uh participation which is not not always
a good thing right we've talked about
Stock Exchange being crap unfortunately
we talked about exorcism iio which is
should get its own video it's also in my
opinion crap because even though it's
official uh it just doesn't cover the
stuff that you need um and and largely
because it's Community Driven right and
so so again that's my number one
complaint against any of these things is
they are not precise enough uh to match
your needs and you can't know that
because until you know what your needs
are so uh there is another um uh there
was another failure and I think that was
um the second failure let me just spit
it out while I'm still thinking of it is
is the technology choices that they pick
for webdev um I remember distinctly and
this was at least four years ago that
when I read through the list of things
that they were having you learn and and
stuff I was like oh no that is like the
worst Choice ever um
and particularly in the area of web
development there are really strong
opinions about what is the best thing to
learn and how should you learn it and
and where can you go to learn it and um
and I personally disagreed with over 80%
of the technology choices that they made
for web development uh I was a web last
time I was a professional web developer
was you know God years ago more than a
decade two decades ago and so you know
don't listen to me about what you should
learn for webd for that you should talk
to someone like learn with Leon or any
number of other people who are regularly
doing it make sure they're actually
employed though if if they're not
employed as a web developer and by the
way what does that even mean right in in
2024 a web developer can mean any number
of things and I did a whole video on
that please go watch it about the type
of web that we're talking about doc web
app web you know broadcast web what what
are we even talking about here um so
when you say you're a web Deb what does
that mean does that mean you know how to
use make documentation with make docs or
does it mean you know how to make apps
apps with react right so so the lack of
specificity in od project and the choice
of Technologies um that is my memory of
it I don't agree with those choice of
Technologies both of those things are
remediated by approaching your learning
in the way that I talk about a lot in
the Boost which is create your own plan
create your own projects create your own
Focus
uh be very very autodidactic about the
thing and personalize the crap out of it
and like somebody mentioned Hunter devs
and that's exactly learned with Leon one
of his major points is that it's
important to distinguish yourself from
all the competition that you take their
boiler P projects or whatever uh if they
exist and you modify them and make them
so that they are indistinguishable from
something that you did for yourself
because you have passion and you want to
do it not because you were checking a
box off on some list here to get to get
a job
and and that is going to count for so
much more in the long term whether and
that's why our first project is a CV you
know a static web doc as a CV because
that's something that everybody has
passionate about and can easily
demonstrate you know that they needed to
do because it shows that they're
maintaining their career and blah blah
blah I mean there's a million reasons to
do it so so that is my conclusion about
Odin project um you know it I think I
think people do things a little bit
backwards what they do is they whether
it be you know a gym
membership or you know uh free C Camp or
Odin project or any of these things I
think they do things backwards this
probably needs a s video but I'm going
to say it anyway and what they do is
they say if I buy this piece of gym
equipment I will get
fit right they don't make a plan for
what they need to do for the to improve
their Fitness they buy the fitness
equipment or the gym membership and they
sort of lazily Or Without Really
engaging think that it's going to fix
the problem and it doesn't and then and
then they're like oh no this gym
equipment is not working and and it's
not a gym equipment it was your plan
you're you got to have a plan you got to
know what you want you got to know what
you want to be you got to know what
you're going after you've got to you
know you know you just got to be able to
visualize that and if you can't do that
I really truly think you're wasting your
time I really believe it and I have
wasted plenty of time uh I've talked
about this so many times um yeah and and
it is true that you know going through
some of these projects to a certain
degree I did this very thing with ocp I
talked about this I was going after my
offensive security project uh my
offensive security certification because
I felt like that would get me in
security industry and then I started
uncovering in the process not by doing
that but bying to other people as a part
of my own plan which included talking to
other people in the industry um that
that wasn't the job I wanted to do and I
I've said this many many times but the
the point is is that um you know in the
sense that free C Camp or OD project or
something like that can may be used to
give you a taste of what it's going to
be like to do those things great but I
really believe if you spend more
time uh doing the other things about
which there's been tons of videos I've
made about
um knowing who you want to be know
thyself right knowing what you want to
do every day what are the specific
activities you want to do every day is
it webd is it working on a computer do
you like to type can you type you know
what are your abilities we talked about
skills abilities or ask you know
abilities skills and um and knowledge
the other day you you need to do this
assessment and when you do that
something like the Odin project becomes
becomes less relevant right because Odin
project a recipe book recode camp you
can look at these you know schmorgus
Borg of educational resources that are
out there and you can zoom in on the
pieces that you need and you can put
them in your plan and now you're in
control of the plan oh bye say hi love
you by um so that's what I'm saying my
wife's just headed off to work so that's
my the point is the Odin project in my
opinion has a lot more I mean if I saw
it on the Buffet of educational
resources that I'm going to put into my
onto my plate right there's a lot more
that I would be dishing up from Odin
project than free code camp and I like
that analogy I'm going to stick with
that maybe I'll make a video about that
because because that's it I mean the odm
Project's got it's got a lot more things
that I would put on the plate um but you
know you you're going to need to make
those evaluations for yourself you're
going to need to I think you're going to
need to start making your own SK skill
stack there's another video about that
please go to skill. IO SK I LS ak. and
the stuff for the first stage starting
your Tech Career please make sure that
you watch those boring videos about how
to get started down the path because so
many people are going to get started
incorrectly by as I said buying the gym
equipment first and then deciding what
kind of what they wanted for their body
later and not knowing that you know they
might have needed one type of gym
equipment versus another you know
because they didn't know up front they
just oh I'll just buy this thing and
it'll make me healthy because that's
what they told me in the advertising
right and and that I mean that's a
horrible extreme example but the point
is the same you are still going to be in
charge and you need to take
responsibility for taking charge and and
I I think that's probably all I should
say about that I keep H hampering on
that part um if found that after I did
all this work and brought all these
courses that I hate that I that I hated
Webb but now you know you hate webdb
right look I worked in a career in webd
I was Nike's Web Master for God's sake
and and I realized that I wanted to do
the backend development more and it took
going through that to realize that right
so chalk it up to experience but but the
rest of you watching this video just
know that a lot of US veterans out there
have wasted plenty of time trying to
figure out what it is that we want to do
in terms of a career and the the the odm
project is just one piece of of the menu
uh that you can go look for look for
this video is going to I'm going to
refer to this video in other videos as
well because of that um and you know
you're in charge so odm project is good
um has it has more nutrients how about
that it's not junk food it's not
educational junk food but you
know make sure you you know pick wisely
when you are choosing your meal